改编自真实事件
第一天
2018年6月23日 星期六
抢断他 小柴
Tackle him, Chai.
你可以的 小柴
You can do it, Chai.
来吧 小柴 我们去吃点东西
Come on, Chai. Let's go eat.
泰国清莱府班宗
嘿 普雷姆
Hey Prem.
你妈妈为你的生日派对 准备了一个海绵宝宝蛋糕
Your mother bought a SpongeBob cake for your birthday party.
小孩子才吃海绵宝宝蛋糕
SpongeBob cake for a little boy!
别再捉弄我了
Stop giving me a hard time.
猜猜我们要去哪里
Guess where we're going?
我们在派对开始前 去洞穴探险吧
Before your party, let's go to the cave.
对 寿星仔的洞穴探险之旅
Yeah, the cave for the birthday boy!
我们来比比谁更快到达公园
I'll race you to the park.
那我最好跟你们一起去
Then I better go with you.
我们应该抓紧时间 天快黑了
We have to go quickly, it'll be dark soon.
教练 我爸在准备派对的食物
Coach, my dad's cooking for the party.
我答应过他会帮忙
I promised to help.
你真是个孝顺的好儿子 那我们派对上见
You're a good son. See you at the party.
好的 慢走 今晚7点见
Okay, bye. See you at 7pm.
睡美人洞 坤喃朗农皇家森林公园
走吧
Go! Go!
等等 阿姆
Hey, Arm!
走吧
Go!
下午3点07分
3号洞室 距离入口800米
走吧 慢慢来
Go, walk slowly.
这是最惊险刺激的一段
This is always the best part.
继续向前
Keep going!
晚上7点32分
我有叮嘱过普雷姆 让他结束练习后直接回家
I told Prem to come straight home after practice.
好吧 如果他们去了你那边 告诉他们我们正在等他们回来开始派对
Well, if they stop over tell them we're waiting to start the party.
不好意思 我来晚了
Sorry I'm late.
店里实在太忙了
The shop got really busy.
你是小柴的妈妈 对吧
You're Chai's mom, right?
是的
That's right.
虽然我很想看他们比赛 但我总是忙于工作
I want to watch the games but I'm always working.
再见
Bye.
看来他们去了洞穴那边
Looks like they did go to the cave.
- 他们全都去了  - 对
All of them?
在这种大雨天
In this rain?
早些时候没有下雨
It wasn't raining earlier.
那个 我想说
Excuse me.
我们应该开车去洞穴那边接他们吧
Shouldn't we drive to the cave and get them?
他们在回来的路上会被淋湿的
They'll get soaked riding back.
这么晚还待在洞穴里 他们到底在想什么
What are they thinking staying in the cave this late.
天气预报说泰国北部有大雨
Heavy rain is forecast in Northern Thailand
因为雨季提前到来
as the monsoon season starts early.
雨季
Monsoon?
通常要到7月才开始吧
That usually starts in July.
不可能是雨季的原因
It can't be the monsoon.
那个洞穴每年都会发洪水
That cave floods every year.
小柴的自行车
That's Chai's bike!
我们是之前联系过你的父母
We're the parents who called ahead.
- 有没有看到那些孩子  - 我们找过了 但无法继续深入寻找
Have you seen the boys? We've looked and can't go any further.
洞穴被水淹了
The cave's flooding.
我们已经联系了当局
We called the authorities.
洞穴淹了 孩子们怎么出来
It's flooding. How can the boys get out?
我已经寻求帮助了 请耐心等候
I've already asked for help. Please wait.
我们进去找他们吧
Let's go in and get them.
请冷静下来 等待支援
Calm down and wait for help.
小柴
Chai!
小柴 能听到我说话吗
Chai! Chai! Can you hear me?
小柴
Chai! Chai!
我刚准备吃晚饭
I just started my dinner.
很抱歉 府长
Sorry, Governor.
通知海豹突击队了吗
Have the SEALs been deployed?
他们已到达现场 长官
They're already on the ground, sir.
凌晨12点47分
- 就是他们  - 是的
- Is that them there? - Yes.
- 你好 - 你好
这位是弗恩昂斯沃斯
This is Vern Unsworth.
我是这个府的府长 你是
I'm the Governor of the province. You are?
我是安隆苏利翁队长
Captain Arnont Sureewong.
隶属海豹突击队
Navy SEALs, sir.
把所有东西搬到帐篷里
Move everything to the tent.
我想知道最新进展
I need an update.
我的队员将会带上潜水装备进入洞内
My men will enter with scuba gear.
这边请
This way, please.
这位先生住在附近 了解这个洞穴的结构
This man lives nearby, sir. He knows the cave.
- 你好 - 你好
Hello.
我画了它的结构图 完整的结构图
I've mapped it. All of it.
我从未在它淹水时进去过
Now, I haven't been in when it's flooded.
那完全是另外一回事 只有狂热分子才会这么做
It's a whole 'nother game. You have to be a bit nuts.
不过 虽然里面有些角落非常狭窄
But, look, there's some pretty tight corners in there.
极度狭窄 但也有些大的洞室
A real squeeze. But there are some big chambers too.
- 请让我把这个拿去给队员看 - 我们走吧
Let me show this to my men. Please. Let's go.
长官 我去给你弄点吃的
Maybe I could find you something to eat, sir?
谢谢你
That would be kind.
这可能会是一个漫长的夜晚
This could be a long night.
从这里开始铺设引路绳
Start laying guideline from here.
3号洞室 距离入口800米
这是个很深的洞穴 长达数公里
It's a deep cave, several kilometers long,
沿途有一些狭窄的通道
with some narrow passages.
如果孩子们进入了洞穴深处 救援时间可能需要延长数小时
If the boys have gone a long way in, it could take several more hours.
但我完全相信海豹突击队的能力
But I have every confidence in the Navy SEALs.
凌晨5点06分
- 你好 府长 - 你好
Hello, Governor.
海豹突击队出来了
The SEALs are coming.
我们找不到孩子们
We couldn't find the boys.
我们遇到了骤发洪水
We hit a flash flood.
里面能见度为为零 可操作空间非常有限
There's no visibility or space to maneuver.
水流太强了 且变化无常
The currents are too strong and shifting.
足球队目前已被困两天
It's been two days since the Wild Boars football team got trapped in the cave.
第2天 6月24日 星期日
泰国当局已调动一百多个政府机构
Thai authorities have activated over one hundred government agencies.
展开一场惊心动魄的国际救援行动
In an astonishing nationwide effort to rescue the boys,
志愿者也纷纷加入到救援行动 不停地从洞穴中抽水
volunteers have also joined the effort, pumping water out of the cave.
政府面临的压力越来越大 他们必须采取一切必要手段救出这些男孩
There is mounting pressure on officials to help these boys by any means necessary.
部长
Minister.
府长 告诉我最新的情况
Governor. Bring me up to speed.
他们已经在抽水了
Pumping has begun, Minister.
这个我知道
I know that.
使用全区最大型的水泵
With the largest pumps in the region.
是我亲自下令采购的
I ordered them myself.
潜水员还无法进入里面
So far the divers have been unable to get through
水位太高了
as the water is so high.
被洪水淹没的区域非常狭窄 难以行进
The flooded sections are very narrow and difficult to navigate.
水流太强了
The current is very strong.
你们还没找到那些男孩 也不清楚他们的位置
You haven't found the boys? And you don't know where they are?
甚至不知道他们是否还活着
Or even if they're alive?
我知道你下周就要调任了
I know you were to be transferred out next week
但在这一切结束之前 你将继续在这里担任府长
but you'll remain here as Governor until this is done.
- 有人跟我说您最了解这座山 - 当然了
They tell me you're the guy who knows this mountain best. Sure.
您知道洞穴被淹了 有一群男孩被困在里面吧
You know the cave is flooded. There are boys trapped in there.
你是谁
Who are you?
我叫萨尼特纳逖斯里 是来自曼谷的水利工程师
Thanet Natisri, I'm a water engineer from Bangkok.
政府派你来的吗
The government sent for you?
不 我是自己来的 就像其他人一样
No I just came, like everyone else.
没时间再等下去了 救援工作刻不容缓
There's no time to wait for help from the officials.
雨水正逐渐淹没洞穴
The rain water is flooding into the cave.
水是从上面来的 不是下面
It's coming from above, not below.
我们必须阻止雨水进入洞内
We have to stop it getting in.
我得找到所有落水洞 并对其进行导流
I need to find all the sinkholes and divert them.
我知道很多这样的洞
I know many like this.
第5天 6月27日 星期三 英国考文垂
什么事 约翰
Yeah, John?
里克 你有关注泰国发生的那件事吗
Uh, hey, Rick, you following what's happening in Thailand?
一群孩子被困在某个山洞里
Some kids stuck in a cave.
是吗 没怎么关注 怎么了
Yeah, no, not really. Why?
他们是怎么进去的
How did they get themselves in there?
不知道 新闻上没说
Uh, I don't know. Doesn't say.
他们能走进去 就能走出来
Well, if they walked in, they can walk out.
泰国政府收到了一份救援潜水员名单
The Thai government's been given a list of rescue divers.
我们在名单上
We're on the list.
那是什么洞穴
What cave is this?
睡美人洞
Uh, Tham Luang.
马修 应该是你妈妈来了
Hey, Matthew, that'll be your mum.
- 马修 - 知道了
Matthew. Okay, okay.
弗恩在两年前绘制了它的地图
Vern mapped it a couple of years ago.
好的
Yeah, yeah.
找到了 在北部
Got it. Up north.
就是它 没错
That's the one. Yeah.
这只是个观光洞穴
It's just a tourist cave.
看起来简单 但弗恩说 当它被水淹没时 根本无法进入
It looks easy, but Vern said when it's flooded, it's impossible.
- 那是对弗恩来说 - 对
-Impossible for Vern. -Yeah.
- 拿好你的东西 好吗  - 好的
Get your stuff together, all right? - Okay.
他们派了好几个团队上山
Well, they've got teams climbing all over the mountain.
在上面钻孔 搜寻…
They're drilling holes and searching--
孔
Holes?
- 稍等一下 - 钻孔 他们不需要我们
-Rick, one second. -Drilling holes? They don't need us, John.
- 这次又是哪里 爸爸  - 泰国
-Where's it this time, Dad? -Thailand.
东西都拿好了吗
You got everything?
- 拿好了 - 真的 来给我一个拥抱
-Yep. -Yeah? Give us a hug.
- 回头见 - 来吧 马修
-All right. See you later. -Come along, Matthew.
再见
See ya.
谢了 如果我要去 我会告诉你的
Thanks, Annabel. I'll let you know if I have to go.
- 好的 - 抱歉
-Okay. -Sorry.
- 再见 爸爸 - 再见 儿子
-Bye, Dad. -Bye, son.
里克 如果你不想去 我可以去找杰森
Rick, look, if you don't wanna do it, I'll just call Jason.
如果你想和他一起去 那就打给他呗
Just call Jason if you'd rather go with Jason.
我没有这么说 我更希望能和你一起去
I didn't say I'd rather go with Jason. I would rather go with you.
先确认一下
Just to confirm,
目前还没有人通知我们去吧
no one's actually asked for us yet?
没有 弗恩只是报上了我们的名字
No, Vern just gave them our names
我们应该做好准备 以防他们找我们 你可以先打包好行李
and, you know, we should be ready in case they do ask for us. Maybe start packing
如果你要来的话
if you think you're coming.
我甚至都不喜欢小孩
I don't even like kids.
好吧 里克
Okay, Rick.
这是一次大规模的救援行动
This is a massive rescue operation
聚集了来自世界各地的一千多名志愿者
with over a thousand volunteers from all over the world.
除了泰国的志愿者外 还有来自中国
Thai volunteers are joined by volunteers from China,
日本 美国 英国和澳大利亚的志愿者
Japan, America, Britain and Australia.
为了降低水位
In order to reduce the water levels,
泰国军方和志愿者们正在争分夺秒地
Thai military and volunteers are working around the clock
将洞中的积水排出
to pump water from the cave.
由于洞中的积水情况越发恶劣
Due to worsening conditions inside the cave,
所有救援潜水工作均已暂停
all rescue dive efforts have been put on hold.
各位 很抱歉 但我们只能从这里步行过去了
Hey, guys, I'm sorry, but we will have to walk from here.
还有奶油饼干吗
Got any custard creams left?
- 只能吃一块 好吗  - 好的
Just one, okay? Yeah.
谢谢
Thanks.
你吃了两块吗
Did you take two custard creams?
没有啊
No.
你吃了
Yes, you did.
你一次吃了两块 真是孩子气
You took two at once. You're like a child.
- 我孩子气  - 伙计们
-I'm like a child? -Okay, guys.
你们先到洗衣房左侧的楼房内 我去拿些氧气瓶 然后就去跟你们会合
It's the building on the left, next to the laundry. I will get the tanks and meet you there.
- 好的 谢谢 - 好吗
-Okay. Thank you. -Okay?
在世界杯H组的比赛中 波兰队以1比0战胜了日本队
In World Cup Group H, Poland beat Japan by one goal to nil.
我们现在该做些什么
So, what do we do now?
做我们该做的事
We do what we came to do.
进入那个山洞
Go in that cave.
说真的 我在乎的不是那几块奶油饼干
Seriously, I mean, I don't care about the custard creams,
而是像我跟我儿子说的 我在乎的是信任
but it's like I tell my son, I care about trust.
我对你很失望 里克 不过没关系
And I'm disappointed, Rick. But that's okay, that's okay.
洞穴已经封闭了
The cave is closed.
不 我们就是为了进去才来的
No, we're meant to go in. The cave is closed.
我们刚从英国大老远赶过来
We just flew all the way from England.
有什么能帮到两位吗
Can I help?
你好
Hello.
我叫里克斯坦顿 这位是约翰沃兰森
I'm Rick Stanton, this is John Volanthen.
我们是泰国政府请来的帮手
We've been flown in by the Thai government to help.
- 你们是英国军队的人  - 不 是英国洞穴救援委员会
You are British army? No. British Cave Rescue Council.
- 我们是志愿者 - 洞穴被淹了
We're volunteers. The cave is flooded.
- 对 我们… - 约翰
- Yeah, we... - John.
嘿 弗恩 我们似乎遇到了一点问题
Hey, Vern, there seems to be a problem here.
他们说洞穴被封闭了
They're telling us the cave's closed.
里面的情况越来越糟 他们把所有人都撤出来了
Yeah, well, it's getting bad in there. They're pulling everyone out.
这两位正是你需要的帮手
These are the men you want.
- 是我向府长推荐的他们 - 府长
I gave the governor their names. The governor sent for them?
长官 看看他们
Sir, look at them.
他们只是业余爱好者 面对洞内的水流 九死一生
They're amateurs. They'll never survive the currents in the cave.
不 他们在世界各地 执行过各种洞穴救援任务
No, no, no. They've done cave rescues all over the world.
我们的名字肯定在某份名单上
Our names must be on some list somewhere.
我跟府长说了 “他们正是你需要的人”
I told the governor, "These are the men you need."
那些孩子还被困在里面呢
- Look, guys, the children are still in the cave, yeah?
- 约翰 等一下 - 就是 时间不等人
-Look, John... -Yeah, but... Just a sec. The clock is ticking.
他们不想看到有外国人死在里面 那样他们会很难堪
Look, lads, it's just that they don't want foreigners dying in the cave. It's not a good look.
我们不会死的 我对送死毫无兴趣
We won't die. I have zero interest in dying.
- 你呢 约翰  - 对 我也是
How about you, John? Yeah, same.
如果是府长派他们来的…
If the governor sent for them...
你们可以参与潜水
You can dive.
谢谢
Thank you.
伙计们 你们首先会遇到一连串的小瀑布
Lads, first it's gonna be a series of small cascades,
接着是更深的涉水区间 然后才是第一个潜水点
followed by a deeper wading section before your first dive.
最有可能找到他们的地方 是2公里外的一个大洞穴
Your best chance is a large cave about two kilometers in.
3号洞室 距离入口800米
你没事吧
You're all right.
我稍后跟上 我需要更多的时间来修理这个泵
I'll follow. I need a few more minutes to fix this pump.
- 水位越来越高 - 都快成河流了
The water level is getting high. It's almost running.
钟乳石隧道 距离入口900米
T型交叉口 距离入口1600米
用时3小时50分钟
我们来看一下
Let's have a look.
该死的
Shit!
到此为止 我们最好立刻返回
That's it. We better head back.
等一下 你会说英语吗
Wait, wait. You speak English?
我是修水泵的 但水位上升得太快了
I fix pump, but water come fast.
真见鬼
Bloody hell.
我们得帮助他潜出去
We'll have to dive him out.
- 你会游泳吗  - 会
-Can you swim? -Yes.
把你的面罩给我
Give me your mask.
- 我先带他出去 然后再回来 - 好的
I'll take him out and come back. Okay.
好的 你要通过这个来呼吸
Right. You breathe through this.
呼吸 明白吗
Breathe. Okay?
面罩
Mask.
把脸埋入水里 试一试
Face in the water. Just try it.
我们一起游泳 好吗
We swim together. All right?
开始了
Here we go.
停
Stop it!
帮帮忙
Help!
这边
Over here!
真刺激
That was exciting.
反面意义上的
Not in a good way.
他安全撤离了吗
Did he make it out okay?
是的
Yeah.
你们好
Hello.
我是这个府的府长
I'm the governor of this province.
感谢两位出手相助
Grateful for your help.
我们已经尽可能地深入洞穴内部
We went as far as we could.
没找到那些孩子
Didn't find the boys.
你们到达的最远处是哪里
How far did you get?
T型交叉口
T-junction.
我的团队之前也到达过T型交叉口
The T-junction is the same location my team got to.
那是他们铺设引路绳的最远端
That's as far as they laid their line.
他们是我纳善如流 请来的帮手
I sent for them on good advice.
不管是什么方法 我都想试试
I'm pursuing every avenue open to me.
是 府长
Yes, Governor.
等救援行动恢复 我会通知您的
I'll let you know when the rescue operation can be resumed.
务必请两位
I must ask, please,
不要在未经我同意的情况下再次进入洞穴
do not go in the cave again without my permission.
稍等一下 伙计们
Just a sec, boys.
长官
Sir?
刚刚那是怎么回事
What was all that about?
理论上来说 这里的负责人是府长
Well, in theory, the governor's in charge,
但负责现场的海豹突击队队长安隆 不愿听命于一个平民
but Captain Arnont's the Navy chief on the ground and he doesn't take orders from civilians.
据传这位府长被革职了
Plus, the rumor is, the governor's been sacked.
原本下周就卸任 现在他却被告知要留下来
This was supposed to have been his last week here, and now he's been ordered to stay on.
以防他们需要一个背锅侠
Just in case they need a fall guy.
弗恩 那是什么
Hmm. Hey, Vern. What's all that?
那是个神龛 上面供奉的是沉睡的公主 朗农公主
That's a shrine to Princess Nang Non, the Sleeping Princess.
这是她的山 朗农山
This is her mountain. Nang Non mountain.
据说从远处眺望这座山 看起来就像一个沉睡的公主
They say when you see it from a distance, it looks like a sleeping princess.
他们说是她的眼泪困住了那些孩子
They say that her tears trapped the boys.
- 沉睡的公主生气了 - 生气了
The Sleeping Princess is angry. Angry?
- 她在生气什么  - 不知道 当地人是这么说的
What's she angry about? I don't know. It's just what the local people say.
第7天 6月29日 星期五
危及生命的感染是一个问题
Life threatening infections are a concern.
别忘了
We need to remember
他们每一次呼吸都会增加二氧化碳的含量
that every breath they take increases carbon dioxide levels.
随着氧气减少 体力消耗会变得越发明显
As oxygen decreases, physical exertion becomes more taxing.
就是这里 那是他们的帐篷
Right here, that's their tent.
- 萨曼  - 你好啊 队长
Sam! Hi, Captain.
- 你不用工作吗  - 我请假了
You're not at work? I took a vacation.
这么说你从工作中脱身了
So you broke free?
我厌倦了天天看你的新闻
I got bored of watching you on the news.
各位 这是萨曼
Hey team, this is Saman.
他也是我们的兄弟 跟了我十年之久
Saman's one of us. He served under me for ten years.
我们当年可是一起抓过海盗的
We chased pirates together.
我带了我的旧潜水装备来
I brought my old scuba gear.
我想帮忙
I want to help.
欢迎之至
Welcome.
打扰一下
Excuse me!
我可以跟您说几句吗
Can I talk with you please?
长官
Sir,
我的孩子在山洞里
my boy is in the cave
现在里面洪水漫灌
and now it's flooding.
我不知道我儿子是死是活
I don't know if my son is alive or dead.
我只求各位长官
All I ask from you, sir,
能帮我找回他的遗体
is to bring me his body.
打扰一下 府长
Excuse me, governor?
我是查理霍奇斯少校 驻扎在冲绳的美国空军
Major Charlie Hodges. US Air Force, Okinawa.
- 这位是奥利维亚塔夫脱上尉 - 你好 府长
This is Captain Olivia Taft. Governor.
我们是离这里最近的特种作战部队
We're the nearest Special Operations Squad.
我们有医护人员 通讯员 后勤专家
But we have medics, comms, logistics experts.
- 我们会尽我们所能地协助救援 - 谢谢
We'll do whatever we can to help. Thank you.
- 谢谢 - 不客气
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
谢谢 各位
Thank you. Everyone!
我们要开始了
We're going to get started now.
我们认为孩子们当时正朝着这里走去
So, we think that the boys were heading for here.
他们称之为芭堤雅海滩
They call it Pattaya Beach.
由于洞内水位高 能见度低
With the high water level and the low visibility,
加之洞穴本身崎岖险要
and the difficulty of the cave itself,
我们的潜水员无法到达他们所在的位置
our divers were not able to reach them.
所以现在的问题是
So, now, the question is,
什么时候再次进洞
when do we go back in?
由谁来进洞
And who is going in?
我们得等到大雨停歇 水泵把水抽出来
We need the rain to stop, and let the pumps do the work.
然后才能进去
And then, we go in.
我们现在就可以进去
We can go in now.
恕我直言 你们接受的潜水训练 针对的是开阔水域
Yeah. No offense, but you're trained to dive in open water,
而不是密闭空间
not confined spaces.
里克和我在类似的洞穴里潜水已有30年了
Rick and I have been diving in caves just like this for 30 years now.
深洞潜水要求潜水员具备一定的心理素质
It takes a certain kind of mindset for the deep cave diving.
掌握呼吸技巧 特别的移动方式 与普通潜水截然不同
Breathing techniques, special ways of moving. It's just different.
我只对我的部下负责
I'm responsible for my men.
至于其他人
As for anyone else,
还得看府长的决定
that's for the governor to decide.
所有人暂时不要进去
No one will go in for now.
等待雨停 谢谢
We'll wait for the rain to stop. Thank you.
第8天 6月30日 星期六
我们需要给每个落水洞修建堤
We need to build dams for every sinkhole.
他好像是自己一个人来的 府长
Seems like he just showed up on his own, sir.
和他一起工作的人是当地村民
The men working with him are local villagers.
我们应该没见过吧
I don't believe we've met.
我是做水利工程的
I'm the water guy.
你是美国人
You are American?
虽然我家在美国伊利诺伊州 但我是从曼谷过来的
I live in Illinois but I'm from Bangkok.
我听说这件事的时候 刚好在曼谷
I was in Bangkok when I heard the news.
我召集了一些志愿者来到这里
I rounded up some volunteers and here we are.
我是这里的府长
I am the governor.
请告诉我你能提供怎样的帮助
Tell me how you can help.
好的
Of course.
由无数山涧形成的网络 携带着大量的雨水
There's a network of mountain streams
通过各种地面缝隙和裂缝流入洞穴内
carrying water through all the fissures and cracks into the cave.
从而汇聚成强大的水流
That's what's creating the strong currents.
如果我们能找到一种方法 来进行导流 水位就会下降
If we find a way to divert these streams, the water level will drop.
那正是我们不停抽水的目的
I thought that's why we're pumping water out of the cave below.
不 府长先生 那些泵根本不管用
No, sir. Those pumps are useless.
洞穴在底部 水会不断流入
The cave is at the bottom, water will keep running in from above.
你能阻止这点吗
Can you stop that?
我们正在努力尝试
We are trying.
不过这是要付出代价的
But there's a price to pay.
你们都进过那个洞穴
You've all been in the cave.
应该知道水是从山上流下来的
You know how the water comes in from the mountain above.
现在我们想将水导流到山体一侧
Now we want to divert the water down the side of the mountain,
让水流远离洞穴
away from the cave,
流入你们的农田
onto your fields.
我们会失去庄稼吗
We will lose our crop?
是的
Yes.
这样就能救那些男孩吗
This will save the boys?
说实话 我无法保证什么
Honestly, I can't promise anything.
但这会为给孩子们创造一线生机
Um... But it will give the boys a chance.
我们同意了
Agreed.
为了那些孩子
For the boys.
随着期盼已久的停雨窗口期到来 大家都认为
With this much-needed break in the monsoon rains, consensus among the many volunteers here is
第9天 7月1日 星期日
寻找孩子们和教练的工作应该很快就会恢复
that the search for the boys and their coach may soon resume.
让家属感到沮丧的是 没有人知道那会是什么时候
The frustration for the families, though, is that nobody seems to know when that might be,
甚至是如何展开救援
or indeed, how it will take place.
距离他们首次进入 这个巨大的洞穴系统已过去九天
Nine days after they entered this huge cave system,
现在的问题依然是他们是否还可能…
the questions remains as to whether the boys can still be rescued.
假设他们在里面还活着
Suppose they're alive in there.
对他们来说那会是怎样的感受
What's it like for them?
为什么这么说
Why say that?
我只是有点好奇
I was just wondering.
我几乎都能看见她了
I can just about see her.
朗农公主
Princess Nang Non.
我们刚收到消息
We've just received word
一项导流作业正在进行中
that a water diversion operation is underway.
志愿者正在筑坝和铺设管道
Volunteers are building dams and positioning pipes
把山上的水流引导至田地
in order to redirect the water from the mountain into the surrounding fields.
救援队希望能以此减少流入洞中的水
Rescue teams hope that this will limit the flow of water into the cave
让水泵得以降低洞内水位
and allow the pumps to reduce the water levels inside.
我去问了古巴高僧能不能来 而他已经来了
I asked if Kruba could come and he's here already.
你能把这些拿去给古巴高僧吗
Lek, Lek. Can you take these to Kruba?
打扰一下
Excuse me.
可以请您加持一下这个吗
Kruba, please could you bless these for me?
谢谢
Thank you.
我听说水泵正在工作 雨也停了
I'm told the pumps are working and the rain has stopped.
海豹突击队什么时候可以进去
When can the SEALs go in again?
要等水退去 至少需要24小时
For the waters to recede, at least twenty-four hours.
英国的潜水员已经准备好进去了
The British divers are ready to go in.
我们的队员正在做准备
Our team is preparing.
现在让他们进去太冒险了
I think it's too risky to let them in now.
他们是在这种条件下潜水的 世界级顶尖潜水员
They're amongst the best in the world at diving in these conditions.
让他们当侦察兵
Let's use them as scouts
先进去看看情况吧
and see what happens?
府长
Sir,
部长让您给他汇报最新情况
the Minister requests an update.
第10天 7月2日 星期一
拍下视频
Video.
如果你们通过了T型交叉口的话
If you get past T-junction.
拜托了
Please,
请务必小心
take care.
T型交叉口 距离入口1600米
用时3小时50分钟
芭堤雅海滩
Pattaya Beach.
有人吗
Hello!
好吧
All right.
我负责左边
I'll keep left.
摸索着寻找尸体
Feel out for bodies.
你闻到了吗
You smell that?
闻到了
Yeah.
好的
Okay.
绳索几乎用完了
Nearly out of line.
嘿
Hey.
他们在这里
They're here.
多少人
How many?
你好
Hello?
- 你好 - 你好
- Hello. - Hello!
- Hello. - Hello.
他们是怎么做到的
How have they done that?
谢谢
Thank you.
英语
English. English.
English?
谢谢
Thank you.
- 你们有多少个人  -13个
How many of you? - Thirteen.
13个
- Thirteen?
他们全都活着
They're all alive.
-13个人  - 是的
- Thirteen? - Yes.
太好了
Brilliant! Brilliant.
我们现在可以出去了吗
Uh, can we go out now?
不 今天还不行
Uh, no, not today.
现在只有我们两个 我们必须潜水进出
No, there are just two of us. We must dive.
但后面还会有更多的人来 没事的
But many people are coming. It's okay.
我们是第一批进来的
We are the first, but... But...
后面还会有更多的人进来 还会有更多
But many will come. Many more.
你们已经在这里待了十天 十天
You've been here ten days. Ten days!
你们很坚强 非常坚强
You are very strong. Very strong.
我们好饿
We are hungry.
我知道 我明白
I know, I know. I know. I understand.
好了 你们先退回去 我们还会再来的
Okay, go back. We will come.
先退回去
Go on back.
你们什么时候来救我们
Uh, what day you come and help us?
- 我们明天就来救你们 - 明天
- We help tomorrow. - Tomorrow?
- 还有更多的潜水员 泰国的 - 泰国的
There are more divers. - Thai divers. - Thai?
我们明天会带上食物 医生和各种物资进来
We'll come tomorrow with food and doctors, and everything.
不要说这种话 约翰 这种事你无法确定
Don't, John. You don't know that.
谢谢
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
- 谢谢 - 谢谢
你们非常勇敢
You are very brave.
你们是怎么做到如此坚强的
How have you stayed so strong?
我们是一个团队 我们互相帮助
We are team and we help each other.
还有我们的教练帮助我们
And our coach help us.
教练
Coach.
让孩子们陷入这样的险境 我向大家诚挚地道歉
I offer my most sincere apologies for leading the boys into danger.
- 不是的 教练帮了我们  - 我们爱我们的教练 他是最棒的
It's not true! Coach helped us! We love our coach! He's the best!
多亏我们的教练 我们才能保持坚强
It is because of our coach we stay strong.
他教会我们冥想
He teach us to, uh, meditate.
- 我们还会祈祷 - 祈祷吗
- And, uh, we pray. - You pray?
- 是的 - 我想也是
-Yes, yes. -I bet you do.
好的
All right.
你们是怎么找到我们的
How... How did you find us?
我们在挖掘
We dig.
为了逃出去
This is to get out?
做得好
Good work.
我们听到山洞里有声音
Uh... We hear a sound in the cave.
- 我们好害怕 - 现在不用害怕了
We are very scared. No need to be scared now.
那只是水的声音 只是洞穴的声音
It's just water. It's just the cave.
- 我也听到了 那只是… - 约翰
I hear it too, it's just... John...
我们应该回去了
We should get back.
好的
All right.
对
Right.
给你
Here.
电池是新的
The batteries are fresh.
谢谢
Thank you.
保持坚强
You stay strong.
祝你们好运
Good luck.
谢谢你们
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
9号洞室 距离入口2500米
用时6小时12分钟
哈喽
Hello!
- 哈喽  - 嘿
-Hello! -Hey!
我们找到那些男孩了 他们还活着
We found the boys. They're alive.
不要随便拿给人看
Careful who sees that.
老头子们找到那些孩子了
The old men found the boys!
- 多少个  - 多少…
Do we know how many? How many of you?
他们找到那些孩子了
They found the boys!
-13个  - 他们都还活着
Thirteen? They're all alive.
真不敢相信
I can't believe it.
他们还活着
They're alive!
13个人
- Thirteen?
- 是的 - 太棒了
- Yes. Brilliant!
他们找到那些孩子了
They found the boys.
- 所有人都还活着 他们都安然无恙 - 所有人都还活着
Everyone's alive. They're safe. Everyone's alive?
他们找到孩子们了
They found the boys!
见鬼 所有人都知道了
Oh, shit. Everybody knows.
消息传得真快
That didn't take long.
里克 约翰 孩子们的情况怎么样
Rick, John, how are the boys doing?
你在哪儿找到了他们
Where did you find the boys?
他们有没有受伤
Are there any injuries?
现在插播一则突发新闻
We're going to bring you some breaking news now.
来自泰国清莱的报道称
Reports coming in from Chiang Rai, Thailand.
两名专业洞穴救援潜水员 退休的消防员里克斯坦顿
Specialist cave rescue divers Rick Stanton, a retired firefighter,
和IT顾问约翰沃兰森
and John Volanthen, an IT consultant,
找到了失踪的男孩和他们的足球教练
have found the missing boys and their football coach.
他们最后一次被人看到是在九天前 随后就被困在洪水漫灌的洞穴内
Last seen nine days ago and presumed trapped in the flooded caves,
12名男孩和他们的教练已确认全部存活
all twelve boys and their coach are now confirmed to be alive.
天啊 这下人更多了
Christ, there's more of 'em now.
来吧 我们该走了
Come on, we should just go.
走吧 直奔小货车
Let's go. Straight to the van.
- 我们先送你们回到里面吧 - 回到里面
Let's move you back inside. Back inside. Back inside.
先回到里面
Just head back in.
拜托了 请给他们腾出一些空间
Come on, guys, let's just give 'em some space, okay?
谢谢 今天大家都辛苦了 多谢合作
Thank you. Been a long day. Can you please comment on US involvement? Thank you very much.
- 谢谢 - 好的
- Thank you. - Okay.
太感谢你们了 你们找到了他们
Thank you so much. You found them.
那些新闻记者确实挺烦人的 你们得适当地应付一下他们
The news guys can be a pain in the butt. You just gotta handle them right.
你要我们说什么
What do you want me to tell them?
“我们找到他们了 现在让我们一起看着他们死去吧”
"We found the boys. Now let's all watch 'em die."
- 好了 里克 悠着点 - 我只是实话实说罢了
Okay, Rick, take it easy. I'm just telling it like it is.
各种抽水作业 淹没田地 向神龛祈祷 屁用都没有
All this water pumping, flooding fields, praying to shrines, it's bullshit!
我接受不了
I'm not having it.
- 泰国的海豹突击队明天就会进去 - 那些孩子绝对出不来
The Thai SEALs are going in tomorrow. Those boys are never coming out.
绝对
Never.
- 我们经验最丰富的潜水员会… - 不 先生 这不是潜水员的问题
Our most experienced divers are going to-- No, sir. It's not about your divers.
我们第一次潜水时 曾经带过一个人出来 他完全惊慌失措
We brought a man out on our first dive, and he completely panicked.
差点就溺水身亡
Almost drowned.
而那只是一次短距离潜水
And that was a very short swim.
你试试带着那些孩子一路潜水出来 那样你会带着他们的尸体出来
You try and dive those kids the whole way, all you'll be bringing out is dead bodies!
- 府长  - 府长
Governor! Governor! Governor!
- 我们先带你们离开这里吧 - 好的 来吧
Okay, let's get you guys out of here. Okay. Come on.
这正是我不想看到的情况
This is exactly what I didn't want.
你知道我们会找到他们的
Well, you knew we'd find them.
但我没想到他们还活着
I didn't expect to find them alive.
现在说什么都迟了
Well, it's done now.
好了 巴斯 我们可以走了吗
Okay, can we go, Bas, please?
第11天 7月3日 星期二
对不起
Sorry.
没关系
It's okay.
他们什么时候会来
When will they come back?
也许他们不会来了
Maybe they won't come.
他们准备好就会来 我们必须做好准备
They'll come when they're ready. We must be ready.
恐惧只是我们的心理作用
Fear is created in our minds.
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes.
让内心归于平静
Let your mind be at peace.
感受呼吸之间 空气的流动
Feel the air you breathe in and out.
吸气
Breathe in.
呼气
Breathe out.
慢慢来
Slowly.
我们正在救援任务的大本营待命
We are standing by at the basecamp of the rescue mission.
救援人员正努力寻找其他途径到达洞内
Rescuers are attempting to find alternative ways to reach the cave.
专家认为孩子们面对接下来三个月的季风降雨和洪水
Experts believe the boys will never survive
生存的机会将十分渺茫
three months of monsoon rains and flooding.
你们还在用以前那款潜水调节器啊
Still using the same Scubapro regulator from my time.
你们第一次潜水时 到达了T型交叉口对吧
On your first dive, you made it to the T-junction?
对 我潜进去的
I did, yeah.
需要给你们简单介绍一下后面的路况吗
Do you want a briefing on the rest of the way?
洗耳恭听 请进
Yeah, please. Come in.
你们之前到达了这里
You made it here.
这里是一段250米的下潜区间 其中有一个狭窄的分支
You have a 250-meter dive here, with a narrow rift,
勉强有肩膀那么宽 连接着7号洞室
barely shoulder-wide, to Chamber 7.
此时你们必须卸下装备
Then you have to de-kit
以手持的方式穿过一段长长的岩架 向着芭堤雅海滩的方向前进
and carry your gear over a long rock shelf to get to Pattaya Beach.
接下来是难度最大的部分
Then comes a tough dive.
这是一条又长又窄的隧道 比这里显示的还要曲折一些
It's a long, shallow tunnel, bit more twisty than this,
长度为350米
350 meters.
能见度为零 还要顶着强劲的水流
No visibility. Pulling against very strong currents.
头顶上方根本没有空间 而且所有拐弯处都有凹槽
No headroom at all. And there's undercuts on all the bends.
这些凹槽十分危险
They're very, very dangerous.
所以你们必须始终保持在较宽的一侧 否则就会被困住
So, you must always keep to the wider side of the line, or you'll get trapped.
穿过隧道后 你们就能抵达孩子们所在的位置
At the end of that, you'll reach the boys.
这样的潜水非常耗费体能
And it's a very physical dive.
所以进去时要尽量保留三分之二的氧气 这样你们才能顺利返回
So, try and save two-thirds of your air going in, so you can make it back.
我们会到达那里的 今天就会去到孩子们身边
We will get there. We'll reach the boys today.
对
Yeah.
大家整理装备吧
Let's pack up.
- 祝你好运 基特 - 谢谢
Best of luck, Kiet. Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you.
祝你们好运
Good luck.
他们会出色地完成任务的
They'll do a good job.
那里面可是我们的孩子啊
Those are our boys in there.
我知道你的部下强悍能干
Look, I know your men are tough,
但这对他们来说不是简单的任务
but it's not gonna be easy for them.
泥泞隧道 距离入口1150米
用时3小时31分钟
狭长隧道 距离入口2300米
用时7小时23分钟
我们是海豹突击队
Navy SEALs.
11天没有进食 这样的状态很不错了
Not bad for eleven days without food.
北方男儿就是强悍
The boys in the north, they're tough.
这里有一些食物和电池
We have a little food and batteries.
每人两口 必须省着点吃
Two bites each. We must save them for later.
我是一名医生
Coach. I'm a doctor.
我给孩子们检查一下身体
I'm going to check the boys.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
阿姆
Arm. Arm.
你很坚强
You're very strong.
洞内的含氧量已不足20%
The oxygen in the cave is below twenty.
我们的氧气只够我们一个人回去
Jay. We only have enough air for one of us to get back.
我们消耗的氧气超出了预期
We used more tanks than we planned on.
你拿着它返回基地
Take it and return to base.
告诉他们这里的含氧量已接近临界值
Report the oxygen meter is close to the red zone.
你明白现在的状况吧
You understand the situation?
我们留下来陪你们
We're staying here with you.
给阿杰拿点水来
Bring Jay some water.
他抽筋了
He's cramping!
第12天 7月4日 星期三
现在你明白为什么部长让我负责指挥了吧
Now you see why the Minister left me in charge.
海豹突击队已到达孩子们身边
Now the Navy SEALs have reached the boys.
在他们为孩子们提供支援的同时
They will support the boys,
我们将会为下一个阶段的救援做好准备
as we prepare for next stage of the rescue.
我向大家保证
I give my word to everyone,
孩子们一定会安然无恙地归来
the boys will come out safely.
府长先生 打扰一下 府长先生
Governor, sir. Excuse me, Governor.
有什么能帮到你吗
How can I help?
请问我可以和府长谈谈吗
Can I speak with the Governor please?
府长现在很忙 我可以代为效劳
The Governor is busy. I can help you.
我们一家是掸邦人 没有泰国国籍
Our families are Shan. We don't have ID cards.
他们还会救助我们的孩子吗 也会救他们吗
Will they still help our boys? Will they rescue them too?
- 一切还好吗  - 她担心她的孩子会得不到救助
Is everything okay? Well, she's afraid her boy won't be rescued.
他们是来自边境附近的缅甸掸邦人
They are Shan from Myanmar, just over the border.
无国籍人士
Stateless.
别担心 他们会把你儿子和其他人一起 从山洞里救出来的
Don't worry, your son will be rescued from the cave with all the others.
你应该为你的儿子感到自豪 他一直非常坚忍
You should be proud of your son. He's been very patient.
府长
Governor!
已经过去12天了
It's been twelve days already.
里面漆黑寒冷 又没有食物
Inside it's dark and cold with no food.
孩子们还能忍耐多久
How long can the boys be patient?
什么时候才能把他们救出来
When are you getting them out?
三名海豹突击队队员正在里面陪着他们
There are three SEALs staying with the boys.
我们打算送些食物进去
We're planning to send food in.
我很明白你的感受
I understand how you must feel.
你怎么会明白
How can you understand?
你儿子快要死了吗
Is your son going to die?
必须得有人想出个办法才行
Somebody's gonna have to come up with something.
里克
Rick.
你在想什么
Whoa. What are you thinking?
只是一个疯狂的想法
Just a crazy idea.
说来听听
So tell me.
里克 疯狂总比束手无策好 我们现在一点办法都没有
Rick, crazy is better than nothing. We've got nothing.
我们可以把哈里找来
We call Harry.
哈里
-Harry?
哈里斯医生
Doctor Harris.
这主意真棒
-That's brilliant.
- 或者说很疯狂 - 又或者…
Or insane.
两者都是
Or both.
- 我不知道他会不会答应 - 虽然我不认识他 但是…
Don't know if he'd do it. I... I don't know the man, but,
我是说…
I mean...
Hmm.
他也许会相信
He might buy that.
他是一名优秀的潜水员
He's a good diver.
是啊
Yeah.
反正我们也需要 更多有能力执行救援任务的潜水员
We could use a couple more divers who can handle rescue work anyway.
我想到了杰森 你知道的
I was thinking Jason. You know?
前提是他没有因为没被邀请而太过生气
If he's not too pissed off that he hasn't been asked already.
也许可以找克里斯朱厄尔
Maybe Chris Jewell.
你觉得克里斯会帮忙吗
You think Chris will be up to it?
大家都说他很优秀
-Everyone says he's excellent. -Mmm-hmm.
杰森说他很强
Jason says he's strong.
那是因为他从未参与过这样的救援
Of course, he's never done a rescue like this.
我会联系他的
I'll call him.
- 好吗  - 好
-Yeah? -Okay.
第14天 7月6日 星期五
克里斯 我来讲解一下
Chris, let me show you.
你的任务是为洞里的人 送去一周的口粮 每人每天一顿
So, you are carrying one meal a day for one week for everyone in the cave.
- 好的 没问题 - 好
-All right. Okay. Yeah. -Okay.
杰森 看着点克里斯 好吗
Jason, keep an eye on Chris, yeah?
好的 他没问题的
Yeah. He'll be all right.
- 他还年轻 还记得年轻二字吗 里克  - 我也不老啊
He's young. Remember young, Rick? I'm not that far behind.
我们带了食物来
We have food.
我们觉得他们也许会想给父母写几句话
Thought the kids might like to write back to their parents.
是的 太好了 谢谢你
Yeah. Good. Thank you.
这里有些写信用的纸
Paper to write letters.
好奇怪
It's strange.
他们的父母都在感谢我照顾他们的孩子
The parents thanking me for taking care of their children.
我还以为他们会责怪我
I thought they would blame me.
没有人责怪你 教练
No one blames you, Coach.
把这些送去给他们的父母吧 是孩子们的亲笔信
Somebody get these to their parents. Notes from the boys.
好的
Okay.
怎么样 我的表现还行吗
So, did I pass?
- 什么  - 我的表现还行吗
-What? -Did I pass?
不 你的表现糟透了
No, you were terrible.
- 你做得很好啦 - 那就好
-You did great. You did great. -Good.
这次潜水相当不容易啊
Well, that's quite a dive.
你打算如何把那些孩子救出来
How the hell do you think we're gonna get those kids out?
我们正在想办法
We're working on it.
…时间所剩无几
Just seconds left on the clock.
内尔马面对那样的防守 无法传球
Neymar couldn't do it with that last check.
哨声响起 比利时击败了巴西
And that's it, the whistle's blown. Belgium beat Brazil.
热门球队被淘汰出局 比利时队顺利晋级…
The favorites have been knocked out of the World Cup. Belgium are through to the semi...
- 我去拿行李 - 谢谢你 巴斯
I'll get the bags. Thanks, Bas.
嘿 哈里
Hey, Harry.
很高兴你能来
Glad you made it.
- 谢谢你的邀请 - 必须的
Mate, thanks for bringing me in. Oh, sure.
- 很高兴认识你 - 幸会
-Good to meet you, Harry. -Well, what a pleasure.
- 旅途愉快吗  - 挺好的
-How was the flight? -Oh, that was pretty good.
获得进入这里的许可证倒是麻烦得要命
It's just, gettin' the permits is a bloody hassle.
- 你想看看那个洞穴吗  - 好啊 这正是我来这里的原因
You wanna see the cave? Yeah. That's what I'm here for.
- 来吧 - 好的
- Come on, then. - All right.
他们的家人从第一天开始就一直守在这里
The families, they've been here since day one.
很难想象他们都经历了什么
Oh, imagine what they're going through.
我们给他们带回了一些孩子们的亲笔信
We managed to bring some letters to them from the kids.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
从这里进去2点5公里左右 就是他们被困的地方
And in about 2.5k, there they are.
就是这里
That's it.
还有谁响应了号召 这里还有哪些人
So, who else answered the call? Who else you got here?
潜水员从四面八方赶来
Oh, there's divers coming in from all over the place.
我们有杰森马林森和克里斯朱厄尔
We've got Jason Mallinson with us and Chris Jewell.
哇
Wow.
最强四人组
The Awesome Foursome.
虽然我和你们不是一个级别的 但…
I'm not in the same league as you guys, but...
但你拥有我们其他人都没有的技能 哈里
But you've got a skill none of the rest of us have, Harry.
- 那是什么  - 他是指你的专业技能
What's that? Well, he's talkin' about your area of expertise.
- 我是一名麻醉师 - 没错
I'm an anesthetist. Right.
不是吧
No.
不行
No!
绝对不行
No, no, no. No.
那是他们唯一的生机
It's their only chance.
里克 这太疯狂了 这样做有违职业道德
Rick, it's insane. It's unethical. It's...
是违法行为 好吗  而且不管怎样 这方法根本行不通
It's illegal, all right? And anyway, it just wouldn't work.
- 你怎么知道 又没有人试过 - 不 你会害死他们的
Well, you don't know that. It's never been done before. No, you'll kill 'em.
反正他们也是死路一条
They're gonna die anyway.
听着 我是说…
Look, I mean...
我们尝试过了
we've tried.
我们什么办法都想过了
We... We've thought of everything.
是啊 所以你们把哈里医生找来了
Yeah, so you called Doctor Harry.
我不是来当孩子杀手的 里克
I didn't come here to kill kids, Rick.
我来这里是为了协助你们营救他们
I came here to help you save 'em.
- 好吧 - 好吗
-Okay. -Yeah?
对 你说得对 我们只是走投无路 一时情急
Yeah, you're right. You're right. I mean, we're... We're just desperate.
- 那是个糟糕的主意 - 对
-It's a bad idea. -Yeah.
- 那是唯一的办法 - 别说了
-It's the only idea. -Leave it, Rick.
哈里是专家
Yeah. Harry's the expert.
他说不行就是不行
If he says it can't be done, then it can't be done.
- 其他我能做的事情 我都乐意帮忙 - 当然
Anything else I can do, -I will do. -Sure.
- 很明显 我宣过誓 我… - 明白
Obviously, I took an oath, and I... Understood.
- 我们会继续想办法的 - 是吗
-We'll just keep exploring. -Yeah?
继续想办法 很高兴你能加入救援
-Yeah. Keep exploring. -Yeah. It's good to have you on board, Harry.
好的
Okay.
里克
Oh, Rick.
随着洞穴内的含氧量下降
As the oxygen level decreases in the cave,
第15天 7月7日 星期六
海豹突击队正加倍努力营救这些男孩
Thai Navy SEALs are doubling their efforts to help the trapped boys.
我们平时呼吸的空气 含氧量大约为21%
The air we breathe contains about twenty-one percent oxygen.
而洞内的空气含氧量已不足16%
The level in the cave is less than sixteen percent.
萨曼 你还好吗
Saman. You okay?
谢谢你让我负责给孩子们送潜水服
Thanks for letting me take wetsuits to the boys.
很高兴你能帮忙
I'm happy you could lend a hand.
乐意之至
I'll help.
谢了 萨曼
Thanks Saman.
钟乳石隧道 距离入口900米
用时2小时57分钟
最近泰国海豹突击队成员萨曼古南的罹难
The recent death
再次提醒了所有人
of Thai Navy SEAL Saman Gunan is reminding everyone
洞穴内部环境的艰险和挑战
of just how incredibly dangerous and challenging it is in the caves.
他是一名训练有素的海军潜水员…
This was a trained Navy diver.
至于萨曼的葬礼
As for Saman's funeral,
政府将会安排一场隆重的葬礼
the government will arrange a funeral with full honors.
救援人员正尝试为最小的男孩
Rescuers are now attempting to source
寻找合适的潜水设备和潜水服
diving equipment and wet suits for the smallest of the boys.
由于没有其他入口 且洞内氧气不足
With no alternate entrances and oxygen running low,
采用潜水的方式将他们救出来 似乎仍然是最好的选择
diving them out still appears to be the best option.
泰国全国上下都在焦急地等待 事件的进一步发展
The entire nation is anxiously waiting for what will happen next.
给我回电话 好的
Call me back. Yeah.
此后海军潜水员最远只会到达3号洞室
There will be no more Navy divers
直至另行通知
going beyond Chamber 3 until further notice.
抱歉 各位
Sorry. Sorry, guys.
嗨 亲爱的
Hi, hun.
天啊
Jesus Christ.
嘿 马修 我是爸爸
Hey, Matthew. It's Dad.
爸爸 你要回家了吗
Dad! Are you coming home?
还得再过几天
Uh, not for a few days yet.
我们听说那边有人死了
We heard someone died out there.
对 一名泰国潜水员 一个叫萨曼的人
Yeah, yeah, one of the Thai divers. A fellow named Saman. He was...
他只是想帮忙 然后就…
He was just helping out, and...
是的 很难过
Yeah, yeah, it's sad.
你觉得你能把那些男孩救出来吗
Do you think you'll get the boys out?
可以的话我们当然会救
We will if we can.
我们正在想办法
We're just trying to figure it out.
虽然这项任务很复杂
I mean, it's complicated,
但我们正努力寻找办法
but we're trying... We're trying to figure it out now.
不管怎样
Uh, anyway,
你最近过得怎么样
how are things with you?
还好吗
You doin' okay?
- 你要来一份吗  - 不用了
Do you want one? Uh, no.
我刚得知我爸进了医院
I just found out my dad's been taken to a hospital.
他们正在给他做检查 他的心脏向来不是很好
So, they're just running a few tests. His heart's never been very good.
听到这个消息我很遗憾
Sorry to hear about that.
他挺硬朗的
He's pretty tough.
他今年已经88岁了
He's made it to 88.
听着
Um, listen.
如果我们有合适的后援…
If we had the right backup,
也许 只是也许
maybe, just maybe
幸运的话 这些孩子当中 或许会有一到三个能活下来
one or two or three, if we're lucky, of those kids might just make it through.
但这可是5个小时的潜水
But you're talking about a five-hour dive.
对
-Right.
这就意味着他们必须在过程中再注射
-That means that they're gonna have to have top-up shots along the way.
然后还有唾液问题
And then you got the saliva problem.
就算面罩能固定住 他们也很有可能会窒息
Even if the masks hold, there's a very good chance they're gonna choke, all right?
这主意太疯狂了 我都不知道我为什么要说这些
The whole thing is insane. I don't even know why I'm saying it.
因为已经死了一个人
'Cause a man's already died.
那些孩子的时间已经不多
-Yeah. -And those kids don't have much time left.
哈里
Harry.
如果我们什么都不做 我们肯定只能捞出他们的尸体
We do nothing, we'll be bringin' 'em out dead for sure.
如果他们是在出来的过程中死的
But if they die while we're bringin' 'em out,
那至少我们尝试过
at least we will have tried.
麻醉
Sedated?
怎么个麻醉法
How sedated?
全麻 全身麻醉
Fully. Fully unconscious.
这是救出他们的唯一办法
It's the only way we can dive them out.
他们必须保持不动 完全不动
They have to be inert. Completely still.
我们会像运送包裹一样把他们运送出来
We'll take them out like packages.
你是一名麻醉师
And you are an anesthetist?
是的 我是
Yes. Yes, I am.
这个不要写下来
Preeya. Don't write this down.
这个方法安全性如何
How safe is this procedure?
我无法回答你这个问题
I just can't answer that.
因为我从未试过
Because I've never done it before.
就我所知 没有人试过
As far as I know, nobody ever has.
理论上来说 有可能行得通
In theory, it could work.
但我们现在说的是
But we're talking about administering anesthetics
在无法监测效果的情况下实施麻醉
under conditions where we just can't monitor the effect.
所以剂量太大 可能会导致呼吸停止
So, too much and respiration can just shut down.
而剂量太少…
And too little and, uh...
一旦他们在水下醒来
If they wake up under water,
他们很可能会溺亡
they can drown.
也就是说 你预计会有伤亡
So, you are expecting, uh, casualties?
是的 我估计会有伤亡
Yes. I expect casualties.
部长 请看这边
Minister, here!
府长
Governor!
部长来了
The minister is coming.
府长 请看这边 府长先生
Governor, over here! Sir!
你们可以实施计划了
The operation may now proceed.
是 部长
Yes, Minister.
愿你们成功
May you be successful.
绝不能让任何人…
No one must know about the...
知道…
你们提出的那个方法
the method you propose.
他们的父母也不行
Not even the parents.
大家尽力而为吧
Do your best.
如果失败了
And if we fail,
我会一力承担所有责任
the failure is mine alone.
好的
Okay.
第16天 7月8日 星期日
你们的志愿服务和努力至关重要
Your volunteering and effort is critical.
在雨季再次到来之前 我们早一点完成水道改道工程
The faster the waterways can be diverted before the monsoons return,
就能为孩子们争取到更多时间
the more time we can buy for the boys.
他们告诉我们这些水坝起到了作用
They're telling us the dams are helping.
让潜水员得以游到孩子们身边
It makes it possible for the divers to reach the boys.
如果我们建造的水坝不够多
But if we don't build enough,
等雨季来临 孩子们会淹死的
when the monsoons arrive, the boys will drown.
…非救援人员 请离开大本营区域
...not involved in the operation, please kindly leave the basecamp area.
请注意
Attention, please.
所有媒体和非救援人员
All media and those not involved in the operation,
请离开大本营区域
please leave the basecamp area.
这是怎么了
What's going on?
是电视台的人和新闻记者 他们全都被撵走了
It's the TV guys, the news guys, they're all being sent away.
以免他们拍到抬出来的尸体
So they don't see the bodies come out.
打扰一下
Excuse me. Excuse me.
抱歉 我听不懂
Sorry, I don't understand.
这些是小柴的妈妈 给你们和孩子们准备的护身符
For you, for the boys. From Chai's mom, Buahom.
- 护身符  - 是的
-Buahom? -Yes, yes, yes.
它们有高僧的加持
Blessed by the holy man.
好的 我叫约翰
Okay. John.
谢谢
Thank you.
来 这是幸运符
Here. For good luck.
- 我不相信运气 - 拿着吧 她正看着呢 快点
Don't believe in luck. Just take it, take it. She's watching, come on.
好的 我们必须在一路上
All right. We'll be having to give them
给他们反复注射氯胺酮
repeat hits of ketamine along the way.
我们给他们注射麻醉剂
We're givin' 'em ket?
是的
Yeah.
你们要隔着潜水服
Now, the injection goes through the wet suit,
把麻醉剂注射进两侧的大腿肌肉
into the thigh muscle here or here.
每一针的剂量大概能维持30分钟
Each dose should last about 30 minutes.
在针口这里留一点空间
Keep a little bit of, see, space on the needle there.
推针 拔针
Push in and out.
很简单
It's quite simple.
但在他们即将醒来的时候
But when they start waking,
你们必须立刻给他们补一针 明白了吗
you guys are gonna have to top 'em up immediately. Yeah?
老大
Boss.
真有你的 杰森
Well done, Jas.
再试一次
Just try again.
祝你们好运
-Good luck.
祝我们所有人好运
Good luck to us all, Captain.
- 约翰 - 队长
-John. -Captain.
祈求森林的守护神
I pray to the Guardian Spirit of the forest
让我代表13个男孩向您忏悔
to apologize for the thirteen boys.
倘若他们有意或无意地冒犯了您
If they have offended you, intentionally or unintentionally,
我在此向所有森林神灵
I apologize to all spirits in the forest.
以及八方神明忏悔
And spirits everywhere.
参与仪式的所有人在此向您诚心祈祷
Everyone at the ceremony would like to pray
请保佑13个男孩
for the thirteen young boys
安全回家
to come back home safely.
5号洞室 距离入口1250米
这是5号洞室 伙计们
It's Chamber 5, lads.
海豹突击队拉了根电线 所以这里有些灯光
The SEALs ran electric cable. Got some lights in here.
才走了一半路程
Roughly halfway.
这些是海豹突击队给孩子们带来的备用氧气罐
These are spare tanks the SEALs brought in for the boys.
收到
Copy.
- 乔希 你和康纳在这等我们 - 好的 伙计 没问题
Josh, you and Connor wait for us here.
Right, mate, yeah.
好的 我就到这里
All right, I stop here.
在第一个男孩通过这段长距离潜水后 我会游过去跟你汇报情况
When the first boy gets through the long dive, I swim to you and report.
如果这个方法行不通
'Cause if it's not working out,
我们必须在带出更多孩子前 及时得知情况
we need to know before we bring any more out.
但如果行得通…
But if it is workin'...
- 那我们就继续 - 对
-Then we get on with it. -Right.
他们是包裹 我们只是送货员
They're packages. We're just the delivery guys.
对
Right.
好了 伙计们 我们开始吧
Okay, lads. Let's do it.
好的 我们走吧
Yep. Let's go.
祝好运
Good luck.
祝好运 哈里
Good luck, Harry.
会有点刺痛
This will sting a little.
就是今天了
Today's the day.
我们会开始把孩子们带出去 一次可以带四个
We're gonna start diving the boys out. We can take four.
他们今天会把我们带出去 但只能带四个
They are taking us out today. But they can only take four.
他们要带我们出去了
They're taking us out.
这是你妈妈给的
From your mom.
得到了古巴高僧的加持
Blessed by Kruba.
- 卡恩医生 - 我是
- Doctor Karn. - Yeah.
这是哈里斯医生 这是卡恩医生
This is Doctor Harris. Doctor Karn.
- 你好 - 你好
Hey.
- 哈里医生 - 卡恩医生
- Doctor Harry. - Doctor Karn.
医生
Doctor, um,
你有必要了解一下我们的计划
you need to know what we're proposing here.
这是给你的
That's for you.
那么你们谁先出去
So, who's going first?
小柴
Chai,
阿姆
Arm,
阿特 潘姆
Aat, Poom.
小柴 你先去吧
Chai, you go first.
好了 来吧
Guess I am first.
好的 把下巴收进去
All right, chin in.
- 不 不行 - 不行吗
- Uh... No way. No. - No?
不行 无法完全密封
No way, it's not gonna seal.
我们会给你再找一个合适的面罩
We'll get you a better mask.
他们要给你找一个合适的面罩
They have to find a mask to fit you.
- 今天吗  - 可能要到明天
Today? Probably tomorrow.
没事的
It's gonna be okay. It's gonna be okay.
我向你保证
I promise.
好孩子
Good lad.
德查 你去吧
Decha, you go.
准备好出发了
Ready to go.
张开嘴巴 德查
Open your mouth, Decha.
举起手来
Arms up.
转一圈
Turn about.
你很快就能回家
You'll be home soon.
他在绑住德查的手
He's tying Decha's hands.
没事的
It will be okay.
别让孩子们看 免得他们看到针头害怕
Don't let the boys watch. There's no need to scare them with needles.
走到前面来 好孩子
Step in front. Good lad.
退后 转过身去
Move back, turn around.
幸运的第一位顾客
The lucky first customer.
来吧 对 慢慢来
Come on. Yep. Steady as you go.
来吧 欢迎来到我舒适的办公室
Here we go. Come into my comfy office.
我叫哈里
Now, I'm Harry.
你是个勇敢的大男孩 是第一个出去的人
And you're a very brave boy, you're number one.
而且你很幸运 有杰森护送你出去
And you're lucky, 'cause you get Jason.
他是世界第一的潜水员
He is the number one diver in all the world.
你想看世界杯吧
Have you been missing the World Cup?
你猜怎么着 巴西被淘汰了
Huh? Well, guess what? Brazil got knocked out, huh?
你以前应该见过这玩意吧 很意外 对吧
You would've seen one of these before. That was a shock, wasn't it?
巴西
Brazil, huh?
猜猜是谁淘汰了他们 是比利时
Guess who knocked 'em out? Belgium.
我猜巴西人应该很不高兴 竟然输给比利时
Bet they're really upset about that. Belgium.
我们来把你救出去 这样…
Get you out of here so that
你就可以看完剩下的比赛
you can watch the rest of the games, huh?
挺厉害的嘛
Tough guy, huh?
针头扎下去都毫无反应
Didn't even feel that one.
慢点 慢慢来
Easy, huh? Easy.
别看
Look away.
下巴固定好了
Good on the chin.
- 好了 你来带他出去吧  - 好的
All right, you wanna take him? Yeah, good, good.
好了 让他过来
All right, good, bring him back.
头向后仰
Okay, his head back.
马上
Most certainly.
- 很好 - 来
- Good. - Yeah.
- 慢点 - 好的
- Slow. - Good.
把那个拉到后面
Let's pull that back.
- 好了 检查一下呼吸 - 好的
All right, check for breathing. All right.
看起来没问题
Looks good.
好的
Okay.
他的呼吸没问题
He's been breathing just fine.
真是太好了
Fucking brilliant.
你没想到会成功
You didn't think it would work?
我也是
Me neither.
好的 我走了
All right. I'm off.
祝你好运
Good luck.
你很幸运 因为你看到那边了吗
And look, you're lucky because see this?
那是约翰 他会护送你出去 他是世界上
That's John. He's diving you out and he is the number one diver
最好的潜水员
in the whole world.
我知道你在这里经历的一切很刺激 但你猜怎么着
And I know it's been pretty exciting for you in here, but guess what?
这届世界杯也挺刺激的 比利时淘汰了巴西
Bit of excitement in the World Cup. Belgium knocked out Brazil.
- 哈里 你给他注射了吗  - 糟了
Harry, Harry. Did you give him the shot? Oh, shit.
我们应该等杰森汇报成功再继续
We were supposed to wait till we heard Jason made it out okay.
对 我已经给他服用了阿托品 只能继续
Yeah. I've done the atropine, and I'm gonna have to... I'm gonna have to keep going.
无须惊慌 没事
No panic. No panic. Yeah.
对 继续吧 我们得继续操作 我可不希望他中途醒过来
Yeah, carry on. We gotta get on with it. I don't wanna risk my boy waking up.
不算太糟糕吧
Not so bad, huh?
- 天啊 对不起 - 没关系
- Oh, man, I'm so sorry. - It's okay.
很好
Good.
基特 你知道这小伙子的名字吗
Kiet, you know my lad's name?
- 阿姆 - 阿姆
- Arm. - Arm?
他是球队的队长
He's the team captain.
好的
Okay.
这个方法行得通
It's working.
天啊
Oh, jeez.
没问题 他准备好了
Yeah, he's good.
我们外面见
See you out there.
- 好 - 好
- Yeah. - Yeah.
祝你好运 克里斯
Good luck, Chris.
5号洞室 距离入口1250米
- 杰森还好吗  - 杰森顺利通过了
- Jason okay? - Jason's through.
好的
Good.
- 小心 - 好的
- Careful. - Okay.
慢慢来
Yeah, easy, easy.
- 慢点 - 好的
-Slow, slow, slow. -Okay.
- 慢慢来 - 新的氧气罐
- Slowly, slowly. - New cylinder.
我再给他补一针
I'll give him another dose.
好的 我接住他了
Okay, so I've got him. Okay.
- 摘下面罩 - 好的
- Coming off. - Okay.
他没事吧
He all right?
- 很好 孩子没事 - 好的 把他搬到这边来
Nice. Boy's good. All right, let's bring him over.
好的 注意脚下 干得好
All right. Step.
- 谢谢 - 不客气
-Thanks. -Yeah.
- 小心 - 好的
- Careful. - Yep.
把他转过来
Turning him around.
好的
Okay.
一 二 三 翻过来
There we go. One, two, three. Turn him over.
不行 他没有呼吸
No, he's not breathing.
不 没事 他还有呼吸
No, he's okay. He's okay. He's breathing.
我们再试一遍
Okay. Yeah. Again.
- 好的 - 好的 慢慢来
-Yep. -Yeah. Slowly.
该死的 他没有呼吸
Fuck! He's not breathing.
不 摘掉面罩
No. Mask off.
- 摘掉面罩 - 慢慢来
- Mask off. - Easy.
慢慢来
- Here we go. - Easy, easy.
对 就是这样 摘掉面罩
Okay. Right, that's it. Mask off.
好的 摘掉了
Okay. Gettin' there.
让我来
Okay, let me in.
好的
Okay...
呼吸啊
Breathe.
快呼吸啊
他恢复呼吸了
Okay, he's breathing.
我每次把他放进水里 他都会停止呼吸
Every time I put him under the water, he stops.
- 你还好吧  - 是的 我没事
You all right? Yep. Okay.
- 戴上面罩 - 好的
Mask on. Okay.
好的 稳住
All right. Steady.
约翰 你还好吧
John, you okay?
是的 我没事 给我一点时间
Yeah, I'm okay. Just give me a minute, please.
- 他的呼吸没问题吧  - 是的
Hey, is he, uh, still breathing okay? Yeah. Yeah.
好的
Okay.
把他带过来吧
Yeah, bring him over.
好的
Okay.
好的 阿姆 轻一点
Okay, Arm. Gentle.
好了 他没问题了
Yeah, he's good.
好的
All right.
- 谢谢 兄弟们 - 不客气
- Thanks, boys. - Cheers.
3号洞室 用时5小时30分钟
好了 快走
Okay, let's go, let's go!
小心他的头
Watch the head!
准备好把他抬过去
Everybody, get ready to take that.
- 一 二 三 - 快点
One, two, three. Faster, faster.
轻一点
Gently.
他怎么样
How is he?
还有呼吸
He's still breathing.
小心他的头
Careful with his head.
氧气来了
Oxygen coming.
- 务必准备就绪 - 还有微弱的呼吸
Make sure you're ready. Got shallow breaths.
好的
Okay!
我们走吧
Let's go, let's go!
生命体征稳定
Vital signs are stable.
好的 慢慢来 别着急
Okay, nice and easy, nice and easy.
慢慢来 伙计们
Easy, guys.
慢慢来 别着急
Nice and easy, nice and easy.
把他送出去
Get him out, get him out.
1号洞室 用时7小时30分钟
有一个孩子出来了
A boy is coming out!
府长让我转告各位 救援行动进展顺利
The Governor asked me to tell everyone the rescue is going well so far.
为什么不能告诉我们名字
Why can't we have names?
恐怕我们目前还不能透露任何细节
I'm afraid we can't release any details.
我知道这对你们来说有多煎熬
I know how hard it must be for all of you
但救援结束后 我们将会第一时间通知你们
but when the operation is complete, you'll be the first to know.
为什么一定要保密
Why does it have to be a secret?
救护车
好的
Okay.
准备 我们准备好了
Ready, we're ready.
对 他没事
Yeah, he's okay. He's okay.
很好
Good.
小心点
Careful.
- 约翰 - 杰森
-John. -Jason.
你还好吧
You okay?
是的 那真是…
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That was, uh...
太不容易了
It's tough.
嘿 约翰
Hey, John.
- 约翰  - 什么事
-John? -Yeah?
- 你没事吧  - 没事
-You all right? -Yeah. Yeah.
只是我负责的那个孩子阿姆…
It's just, uh, my lad was called Arm...
他曾一度停止呼吸
Well, he stopped breathing for a minute.
我还以为他…
I thought he... I thought he was...
但他并没有 他没事
But he's not. He's okay. He's okay.
干得好 克里斯 这并不容易
Well done, Chris. It's not easy.
谢谢你 约翰 谢谢
Thanks, John. Thanks.
医生 医生呢
Medic. Medic?
- 怎么样了  - 四个都出来了 医生
Um, what happened?It was four out of four, Doctor.
- 然后呢  - 孩子们都安然无恙
Four what? All the boys are fine.
做得好
Great job.
是啊
Yeah.
据悉 一支精英潜水队伍正尝试引导男孩子们
We understand that a team of elite divers is attempting to guide the boys
在水下潜泳3公里 游到安全的地方
through a three-kilometer underwater swim to safety.
“游到安全的地方” 这个说法我喜欢
"Swim to safety." I like that.
…这就是他们的计划
今天早上 一个重大的…
你还有奶油饼干吗
Got any custard creams left?
- 没有 - 你还有什么
No. What do you have?
- 全被我吃光了 - 该死的
I ate them all. - Knob.
…已被转移 以便腾出更多空间
- The media were relocated to clear additional space
留给重要的军事人员和志愿者
for essential military and volunteer personnel.
救援行动是秘密进行的…
The rescue operation is shrouded in secrecy...
昨天他们说只要我们能够 成功救出一个活着的男孩 我们就是英雄
Yesterday, they said if we got one boy out alive, we'd be heroes.
现在如果我们救出一个死的…
Now, we bring a single one out dead...
是啊
Yeah.
现场直播 拉希提亚邦通
第17天 7月9日 星期一
所有氧气瓶都提前部署在沿途各个关键位置
The air tanks are all strategically placed along the route.
在昨天的救援中 他们耗尽了所有氧气瓶
During yesterday's rescue, they used every single tank.
清莱府府长称这是“人和水的斗争”
The Governor of Chiang Rai Province called this, "A War With Water."
当地天气预报显示接下来会有大雨
Local forecasting is predicting heavy rain.
不用害怕 里特 知道为什么吗  因为你有最好的潜水员护送
No need to be scared, Rit. You know why? Because you have the best diver.
准备好了吗 向上看
Ready? Look up.
好孩子 看到没 结束了
Good boy. See? All over.
就这么简单
All over.
就是这样 好孩子
There you go. Good boy.
我叫迪尤
I am Dew.
我叫里克
I'm Rick.
再拿些水管过来
Bring down more pipe!
没有了
There's no more!
那是最后一根了吗
Is that the last of the pipe?
我们已经让曼谷那边多送点过来
We've sent for more from Bangkok.
水管不够吗
Need more pipe?
水管
Pipe.
- 是的 他们都很好 - 好的
Yeah, they're good. - Okay.
第六名男孩已上担架
- Sixth is on the Skedco.
据悉 今天有五个男孩被带出了洞穴
We're hearing that five boys have been brought out of the cave today.
最近的天气预报显示 地平线上已形成风暴云
Recent weather reports show storm clouds on the horizon.
雨季正快速逼近
The monsoon season is closing in fast.
- 成功了 各位  - 成功了
Hell yeah, man! Yeah!
给小柴的面罩 从曼谷空运过来的
Mask for Chai. Flown in from Bangkok.
好的
All right.
不
Nah.
- 你觉得会合适吗  - 最好如此 这个要小一些
Think it'll fit? Yeah, it better do. It is smaller.
坐吧 巴斯
Have a seat, Bas.
谢谢
Thank you.
你们在做什么 继续保持这样 好吗
Whoa, whoa, what are you doing? You wanna keep it like that, okay?
好大的雨
That's a lot of water.
第18天 7月10日 星期二
- 里面的水位应该会有所上升 - 毫无疑问
Water level's gonna be rising in there. For sure.
- 我们还是能游过去的 对吧  - 不知道
We'll still make it through, though, right? Don't know.
潜下去就知道了
We dive and we find out.
这得看情况 杰森
It depends, Jason.
里克和我在它完全淹没时进去过 那简直是头猛兽
Rick and I have been in there when it's fully flooded. It's a beast.
别这样 我们可不能现在退缩
Come on. We're not stopping now.
你想死在洞穴内的话 随便你 杰森
You die in a cave if you want to, Jason.
如果不能确保全身而退 我是不会进去的
If I'm not sure of coming out, I'm not going in.
快点
Hurry.
雨下个不停 我们需要更多沙包
It won't stop raining. We need more sandbags.
各位 东边的岩石上有三个落水洞
Everyone, there are three sinkholes in the rocks to the east.
好吧 应该没问题
Okay. We can make it.
- 我们最好速战速决 - 来吧 伙计们
-We better move fast. -Okay, lads.
好的 哈里
All right, Harry.
今天所有人都会离开这里 我们尽量速战速决
Everyone leaves today. We do this as fast as we can.
好的
All right.
- 不行 看到没 这里有空隙 无法密封 - 对 面罩是曲面的
No, see, that's open. It's not gonna seal. Yeah. It's buckling.
我们先把其他人带出去 然后再解决他的面罩问题 好吗
All right, let's dive the others out. Then we'll get him sorted. Yeah?
好的 交给我吧 粉红色面罩 我喜欢
Okay, I got this. It's pink. I like it.
好了 那么下一个轮到谁
All right, so, who's next?
我不会游泳
I can't swim.
我们会活下来吗
Will we survive?
别害怕 我们必须相信他们
Don't be afraid. We have to trust them.
好的
Okay.
好了 转过去
Okay, turn around.
这个小伙子是谁呢
Who have we got here?
- 他叫普雷姆 - 普雷姆
- This is Prem. - Prem.
来吧 普雷姆 我们带你离开这里
Come on down, Prem. Let's get you outta here.
我们最后出去吗
Are we the last to go?
克里斯会负责带你出去
Chris is diving you out.
他可是世界上排名第一的救援潜水员
You know, Chris, see, he's the number one rescue diver in the whole world.
正是我
That's me.
普雷姆 你知道怎么做的 你都看过了
All right. Prem, you know the drill. You've seen this.
往上看 准备好了吗
Do you wanna look up? Ready?
- 好了 - 没问题
All right. Yep.
出发吧
Off you go.
好的 还剩最后一个
All right. One more to go.
你来选吧 向上还是向下看
Your choice. Up or down?
向上
Up.
就是这样 一点都不痛
There you go. That was pretty painless.
我们现在就带你回家 也许还能赶上晚餐
We're gonna get you home. Maybe for dinner.
这已经是极限了 拉得太紧的话 密封圈就会撕裂
It's the best we can do. If I pull it too tight, it'll collapse the seal.
- 还是有点松 - 我们没时间了 水位正在上涨
It's still a little loose. We don't have time. The water is rising.
如果现在不救他出去 他就会永远出不去
If he doesn't come out now, he doesn't come out.
我会尽量避免碰撞的 必要时我可以用手扶着面罩
I'll keep it from bumping. I can hold it if I have to.
你来决定吧
It's your call.
我会游得慢一些 所以你们等我游出一段距离后再跟上来
I'll be going slow. So give me some space before you follow.
孩子们呢 他们安全出去了吗
The boys? Are they out safely?
但愿如此吧 轮到你了
We hope so. Your turn now.
他比那些孩子重不了多少啊
He's no heavier than the boys.
我会紧随你身后
I'll be right behind you.
别跟得太紧
Not too close.
酒馆见
See you at the pub.
- 好的 轮到我们出去了 - 你先走 我们随后跟上
All right. I guess it's our turn now. You go. We follow.
好的 记住一点
Yeah. I mean, remember,
水流比之前强了很多
the current is much stronger than it was.
- 而且这水…你懂的 - 对
-And the water is, you know. -Yeah.
时间越来越紧迫
The clock is ticking,
这给救援队增加了不少压力
putting pressure on the rescue team.
大家都担心倾盆大雨会导致雨水倒灌进洞里
The fear is the heavy downpour will push water back into the cave
志愿者来不及引流山上的雨水
faster than the volunteers can divert the rain from the mountain.
对 再来一个
Yes, one more, one more.
有人吗
Hello?
Hello, hello, hello!
快点 把他的头抬起来
Yeah, come on. Keep his head up.
开始切入下一个
Start cutting through the next one.
准备迎接第11个孩子
Reset for 11.
好的 杰森 我接住他了
Okay, Jason. I've got him.
好了吗 三 二…
Okay? Three, two...
他没事
He's good. He's good.
稳住 伙计们
Steady now, lads.
我们看到人了
We got a visual.
克里斯
Chris.
里克
Rick.
见到你真好
It's really good to see you.
我不知道有没有人能够…
I didn't know if anyone was gonna be able to...
他还活着吗
Is he alive?
- 是的 - 真的吗
- Uh, yeah. - Yeah?
对 是的 他还活着
No, yeah, he is, yeah. I...
我刚刚找不到引路绳
I lost the line back there.
我找到了一根电线 沿着它来到了这里
I found a power cable and followed it here.
- 我不知道这是哪里 - 你还在4号洞室
I, uh... I don't know where I am. You're still in Chamber 4.
干得好
Well done.
给他补一针
Keep him topped up.
你会没事的 等等哈里 他正在过来
You'll be fine. Wait for Harry. He's coming now.
- 让他看看孩子的情况 好吗  - 好的
Let him have a look, yeah? Yeah. Yeah.
你唯一要做的就是照顾好那个孩子 我们会带你出去的
Your only duty is to that boy. We'll get you out.
- 所以做好准备 - 对 好的
So get ready. Yeah. Okay.
给他戴上面罩 一切听哈里安排
Put his mask on and do whatever Harry says is best.
明白了吗
Got it?
我们外面见
See you on the other side.
克里斯在哪儿
Where's Chris?
- 还在4号洞室 - 好的
- Still in Chamber 4. - Okay.
- 教练还有呼吸 - 好的
- Coach is breathing. - Okay.
- 他没事 - 好的
Hey, hey, hey. Mister John. - He's fine, he's fine. - Okay.
轻一点
Easy with him.
教练的状况不错
Coach looks good.
克里斯那边怎么样
How's Chris gettin' on?
他遇到了一点麻烦
He's struggling a bit.
我让他等等哈里
Told him to wait for Harry.
克里斯
Chris?
在
Yeah.
发生什么事了
What's happened?
我弄丢了引路绳
I, uh... I lost the line.
- 你负责的孩子没事吧  - 我想是的 你最好过来看看他
Is your boy okay? I think so. You, uh, might wanna check him.
- 你给他补过针了吗  - 我大约在一小时前给他补过
Did you give him a top-off? Yeah, I gave him one about an hour ago, I think.
- 好的 我们再给他补一针 - 好
Yeah, let's give him another hit. Okay.
需要我接替你完成剩下的路程吗
Do you want me to maybe take over from here?
不用了 还是我来吧
Uh... No, no, no. I should... I should do it.
接下来可是U型弯
It's the U-bend.
好吧 里克说过…
Well, I mean, Rick said, uh...
他说过一切听你安排 所以…
I mean, he just... He said to just do what you said, so...
我认为你已经完成了最困难的部分
Well, I reckon you've done the hardest part.
剩下一小段何不交给我
Why don't I do the last bit?
那样我就可以说我也是救援者之一了
And that way I could say that I was a rescuer, too.
里克说怎么做对男孩最好就怎么做
I mean, Rick just said to do what's best for the boy.
我真心认为那是最好的做法
I really think that that's what's best.
- 好吗  - 对 好的
-Okay? -Yeah. Okay.
水泵快撑不住了
The pump is going!
水泵坏掉了
The pump's gone!
来吧 克里斯 快点
Come on, Chris. Come on.
哈里
Harry!
- 孩子没事吧  - 是的 他没事
Is the boy good? Yeah, he's fine.
- 克里斯呢  - 他就在我身后
How about Chris? He's right behind me.
里克
Rick. Rick!
我去拿些氧气瓶来 我要回去找他
I'm gonna get my cylinders. I'll go back for him.
他很快就会出来
He'll be here.
干得好 克里斯
Nice one, Chris!
- 干得好 - 谢谢
-Well done. -Thanks.
- 我负责的孩子 他是否… - 他还活着
-My boy, is he... -He's alive.
伙计们 我们成功了
We bloody did it, lads!
- 克里斯 你还好吗  - 是的
- Chris, okay? - Yeah.
还有人没出来呢
Not all out yet.
所有人撤退
Everyone out!
水泵要炸了
The pumps are exploding!
皮查伊
Pichai.
很高兴见到你
Good to see ya.
好的
Okay.
干得好 各位
Well done, boys.
干得好 老头
Well done, old man.
做得好
Good job.
- 谢谢你 里克 - 谢谢你 队长
-Thank you, Rick. -Thank you, Captain.
- 干得好 队长 - 约翰
- Great work, Captain. - John.
- 干得好 伙计们 - 谢谢
- Great job, guys. - Thank you.
- 太棒了 - 干得好
- So great. So great. - Well done.
- 感激不尽 - 哈里
- Thank you so much. - Harry.
- 了不起 伙计 - 干得好 各位
- Legend. Legend, mate. - Well done, lads.
各位 引路绳的事我很抱歉 它一直…
Guys, I'm sorry about the... The line. It just kept...
嘿 没事的
Hey, it's okay.
一切都结束了
It's done.
- 救援成功了 - 没事的 克里斯
-Yeah. It worked. -It's okay, Chris.
是啊
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
我以为我只能把他留在那里了
I just thought I was gonna have to leave him in there.
你们都来自不同的地方
You all have come from all over.
有的来自附近的城镇
From the nearby town.
有的来自世界各地不同的国家
Others, from different countries around the world.
你们奉献了自己的时间 专业知识
You have given your time. Your expertise.
有的甚至牺牲了自己的庄稼
Some, even the rice crops.
你好
Hello.
而且你们都不求任何回报
And you ask for nothing in return.
但我知道你们做这一切
But I know that you all did this
都是出于同一个原因
for one reason.
那就是对孩子们的爱
The love for the boys.
没事的
It's okay.
我们没事
We're okay.
谢谢
Thank you.
非常感谢大家
Thank you very much, guys.
府长 你会卸任吗
Governor, will you be stepping down?
不客气
You're welcome.
好的
Okay.
对 好的
Oh, all right. Yeah.
- 嘿 - 你做到了 哈里
Hey. Well, you did it, Harry.
他刚收到他父亲去世的消息
He just got word his dad died.
所有人都到齐了 长官
That's everyone, sir.
除了一个人
All but one.
嘿
Hey.
过来吧
Come here.
小柴
Chai.
你好
Hi!
谨以本片纪念萨曼古南
以及在救援过程中血液遭到感染 后不治身亡的海豹突击队队员
贝鲁特帕克巴拉
在救援行动结束数天后
洞穴彻底被洪水淹没 时间长达8个月
- 说茄子 - 茄子
Say "cheese." Cheese!
志愿者引流了大约五千六百万加仑的水
因此而遭受损失的农民获得了政府的赔偿
没有国籍的教练和三个男孩
获得了泰国政府授予的公民身份
来自17个国家和地区的5000多名志愿者 参与了救援工作
字幕翻译： 梁淑仪
创意监督 罗婷婷